[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
oh the sweet song all right
um welcome everyone to the star wars
i am peter lindbergh the steward of the
stoa stow is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge of this very moment
and no i will never get bored of saying
that intro um
today we have uh matthew seagal
um or siegel um which which should let
me
let me unmute you uh and it's not cigar
i know seagull right
it's a long-standing controversy
actually um
some people say cigar some people some
some people say seagull my mom says
seagull my dad says cigal
they're divorced go with seagull that's
what i go with
sorry it's so complicated no worries i
got both of them so i got both the
mother and the father happy
um and uh matt is uh
coming today to talk on the spiritual
mission of america and the anthropocene
which is a juicy subject matt is an
assistant professor
in the philosophy cosmology and
consciousness program at the california
institute of integral studies
he has a youtube channel that i've been
following
since 2007 um called the thou art that
um like i was into the when i was
younger into the ken wilbur stuff and
not that much people were talking about
ken wilbur
on youtube or online and uh but matt was
like who's this crazy guy i love him uh
and so i've been following him for a
while and so i'm
very happy that he's at stowa today
uh to discuss this topic so how it's
gonna work uh
matt's gonna share his thoughts on the
subject at hand
for about 20-30 minutes if you have any
questions
throw them in the chat i'll call on you
and meet yourself ask at the mat you can
throw them the chat anytime just have
like
cue or question beforehand if you want
me to read on your behalf just indicate
that because this will
go on youtube so that being said uh matt
i will
take in and uh yeah let's begin
awesome all right hopefully y'all can
hear me all right
and that i hope my internet uh
connection holds
i'm actually in oklahoma though i am a
california resident i'm on a bit of a
cross-country road trip at the moment to
uh
well for a variety of reasons but one of
them is to sort of take in this
this great very large country um
if i was being cynical i would call it a
farewell tour but i certainly hope it's
not
um but we're in the midst of
some rough times right now as a nation
as a people um some would ask uh
whether we can even think of ourselves
as a people
uh as americans there's some
a whole variety of competing visions for
what that might mean and
some people who would rather not even be
associated
with the idea of any form of american
patriotism so
we're gonna talk a bit about um
the spiritual potential of of america
and i'm going to yeah take hopefully no
more
than 20 minutes to lay out a vision and
then i want to
hear from all of you about how it lands
and engage in dialogue for the rest of
our time together so um
you know thanks peter and thanks to
everyone who makes the stowa possible
i've uh i've been sort of hovering in
the background
for a while um enjoying uh different
guests that you've had on in different
conversations for a number of months so
it's it's really exciting to be here
so the spiritual mission of america
in the anthropocene um
i was trying to find a juicy title so
i'm glad peter thought
i succeeded in that
why spiritual why spiritual mission um
well i think
as emerson was among the first to point
out uh america has
a tendency to superficiality and indeed
materialism we are money-loving
people and um that's not to say though
that we aren't also a deeply spiritual
people
and i want to emphasize the spiritual
dimension because of
uh the pervasive ideological dominance
of
a variety of forms of materialism you
know there's the values of materialism
that we associate
with say a capitalist political economy
there are the there's the ontology of
like physicalism
in the natural sciences the sort of
metaphysics of materialism
that's less of a sort of value statement
as in the case of
like the capitalist political economy
where you value material
things and it's more of a sense of what
the universe is and i mean
uh materialism and i'm critiquing
materialism in all of these senses
because
in order for us to move forward as a
nation i think we need to appeal to
higher ideals than just the capitalist
bottom line
and uh i think we need to
forge and and re-engage with an ideal
um that i think has always been central
to the
spiritual mission of america this this
ideal of
individuality uh if if the united states
had
one gift uh as a that we as a people i
think
uh and i'm assuming we're all american
here maybe we're not but
um speaking to my fellow americans i
think
this this notion of the individual is
something that
um america i think is
uniquely situated to to help to
um to birth and to give to the world um
it's not it's not the be-all and end-all
of human existence right to be an
individual there are other important
values um that we would need to learn
from other people
and you know so one of the things that i
want to share tonight is this deep sense
of pluralism
that while the united states of america
has its unique spiritual mission so do
all the other peoples uh that we inhabit
this planet with and
uh eventually i think the the
larger vision that i would want to lay
out in the background of the specific
vision for america
is a view of the evolution of
consciousness and a view of
the human being as indeed a work in
progress something we are striving
toward and that every
uh particular whether it's culture or
ethnicity or people
that composes the diverse human family
at the moment
every people has something to contribute
to the realization of this future human
that we have not yet
realized um
so i want to talk about the spiritual
mission of america
in an effort to combat the materialism
that i think
it debases our sense of uh
culture um it commodifies
uh our understanding of everything from
personal identity uh and even racial
identity now is
something that corporations you know the
racial justice movement has totally been
absorbed in and approved by all of the
major corporations
and so i think there are deeper sources
of cultural meaning
that we need to seek out and i also
think materialism debases
our understanding of our nature not just
our culture but our understanding of
race uh for example we have this
rising uh form it's and it's not just
the white nationalists i mean
um all forms of i think fantasy
it's it's you know i don't want to be
too provocative here but it seems to me
to be a sort of
pathological um adolescent male fantasy
of racial purity that sort of
um driving this movement towards
um white nationalism in this country and
and
around the world um and i think that's a
very materialistic understanding of
racial identity
as if it were based on um
genes or or you know again some fantasy
of purity where
you know every biologist that i've
talked to when i ask them to define
what a gene is they give me a different
definition i think it's a
it's a it's an abstraction that uh
follows from a sort of reductionistic
materialist
understanding of the universe and of
biological evolution
um and so i i want to combat this
materialistic
dead weight that's holding um our
culture down
uh move beyond materialism and
uh really take seriously the idea that
yeah each of us as individuals has a
spiritual mission and
um entire peoples nations can have a
spiritual mission
and you know what would this mean in
concrete terms
uh to move beyond materialism well i
think
there's a there's a one of the ways that
materialism comes through in our in our
culture
is uh in the ways that we relate to
death and
i think that this in part drives the
i would call it a religion a religion of
consumer capitalism
that we think this is the only life we
have that our consciousness will
disappear when our bodies die and
decay and perhaps
there's a wider spiritual ecology
that that we are participating in and um
maybe we can take seriously something
like uh
reincarnation maybe um
you know whatever it is that's conscious
in us has been here before in prior
incarnations and will remain
on the earth uh in incarnations after
this particular body
it's a very different vision than the
materialist vision and even the
christian vision where this is the one
life and after this life you just go to
heaven and the drama of
existing in time and history is over um
so you know i think there are profound
political and economic implications to
taking something like reincarnation
seriously
because we may reincarnate as as
different
into different ethnicities in different
lifetimes and i think it helps us
develop a shared sense of humanity which
again is
something i'm trying to gesture towards
here um
so the spiritual mission of america in
the anthropocene
why am i bringing the anthropocene into
this well
if we're able to solve all of our social
and political problems
uh which is a big ask um we still will
have to deal with the ecological crisis
we will still have to deal with the
delusion
of human exceptionalism as if the human
being
is not uh another animal that
evolved out of the earth and shares this
planet with a number of other species
most of which are bacteria
that regulate the atmosphere and
so even if we solve our social and
political problems even if we figure out
how to get along as human beings
we're going to need to deal with the
consequences and repercussions of
century or so of a fossil fuel economy
um i like to call it the petroleum
interval
over the last hundred years or so um
where
through fossil fuel and the energy that
was unleashed by harnessing the power
of fossil fuel um the human population
has shot up
uh from i think it was something like a
billion
um in the late 1800s and now you know
we're pushing
eight billion i think now so that's an
interval
made possible by oil oil is not going to
be cheap and easy to get to
for much longer it's probably already
more expensive to get
oil to market than it is than the profit
you can make from it so
that that brief period of um
hyper expansion of the capitalist
economy is going to come to an end when
whether that's already started or it
happens five or ten years from now it's
inevitable
um and so all of the various
facets of the ecological crisis from
climate change to mass extinction to
um you know losing top soil and on and
on
are going to have an effect on
our ability to maintain political order
uh keep people fed we're going to be
dealing with mass migration
um just in the united states over the
next
couple of decades as the southern part
of the country and the western part of
the country becomes increasingly
unhabitable
uh tens of millions of people are going
to be migrating um
north and how nobody's preparing for
that except the banks and insurance
companies
are now starting to realize that they're
going to take a hit on their investments
if they don't pay attention to climate
change but politically
nobody's taking it seriously um so all
that's coming
in the midst of of increasing social
unrest uh so we got a lot of major
problems to deal with
and i don't have any solutions to those
problems but i have a few
suggestions about um
how we might build a sense of national
solidarity again
as americans and in service to a larger
project
for humanity as a whole
so i think what i want to say about
america is
i think it would classify as a form of
american exceptionalism
i do think the united states is an
exceptional
uh nation um why well i mean it's the
oldest
democracy on the planet and several
people have said this maybe it's a
controversial claim we can talk about it
but it seems to be the first
nation that was founded on ideas or on
ideals ideals like individual freedom
and social justice right these are
written into our founding documents
the united states of america is a
product of the enlightenment
and these ideals from the moment they
were first
you know that pen was first put to paper
uh to write them down uh from the moment
that they were
uh enacted this country failed to live
up to them
and the history of the united states is
deeply tragic
and i think any attempt to to move
forward towards a more unified sense of
national identity is going to need to
acknowledge
the tragedies and the failure to live up
to these ideals
of individual freedom and social justice
um
you know in the declaration um
the founders declared they called it
they said the self-evidence
right that all men are created equal
how is it self-evident that all men are
created equal
i think again this is an enlightenment
ideal about the nature of the human and
the potential of the human
um but from the very moment you know
that document was signed and then the
constitution
uh after the revolutionary war was won
um we failed to live up to the ideal
initially
it was only land owning white men that
right that had their individual freedom
uh protected and that could count on the
courts to
um to secure justice uh if they were
wronged
um and gradually we've slowly
begrudgingly
expanded these rights to include others
but it's been a fight
the whole time um but the beauty of the
country
is in these ideals and i don't think we
can we can or should give up on those
ideals yet
so the country has been
through um three major trials
one per century over its history right
the first one
uh was the revolutionary war the second
one was the civil war
uh the third one was the 1960s 1960s
counterculture the
the civil rights movement and
we're now in the fourth great crisis
of uh american democracy um
i don't know what you want to call it i
think we'll need more historical
distance
from it to fully understand what's going
on
but there are signs of the crisis
everywhere you look
and a lot of people who
maybe identify as liberals or as
democrats they would they would blame
trump for this crisis but trump is
just a symptom um trump is not the cause
uh a lot of people think that the
post-truth era began with trump
uh i think it began with george w bush
or
i mean what president ever really
told the truth about american military
imperialism
um so these problems pre-exist
trump but trump is sort of the crescendo
and the the manifestation of the
american shadow i think
forcing us to confront the tragedy of
our own history and the problems that we
continually have failed
to honestly look at and deal with and so
trump in a sense
as a symptom of this shadow
[Music]
of the united states of america is also
an opportunity for us to finally
look and engage and um
and try to heal from whether it's
genocide
or slavery or you know continued
depression
we've made progress but we're not there
yet
and i think trump is sort of the final
wake-up call that we really need to
um to figure this out to live up to the
potential of the ideals that this
country was founded on
so
i want to speak a bit about um
what the united states the resistance
that
the the american vision is meeting in
the world right now
um alexander dugan was on the stoa
a couple of weeks ago i think just last
week and um
i've only recently been
exposed to some of his ideas and um
initially i was very excited about his
critiques of liberalism
and of modernity in general i share a
lot of those critiques actually but
when i started to learn more about the
alternative that that he wants to
um to push uh i was a little bit more
skeptical
and um you know i think
it's horrible that he's being banned
from all the uh social media platforms
and that he's being
just dismissed as i guess liberals and
the tech companies dismiss him as a
fascist and he's
claims not to be a fascist i'm i'm
kind of skeptical but again um i
i think that uh the approach
that the d platformers and the the
people who would just refuse to even
debate
or or engage in in dialogue with people
like dugan i think
only um further delegitimizes the
the liberal um
it further delegitimizes liberalism as
if you know
um they don't think that the strongest
argument would win
uh and they just want to shut up people
that are criticizing the liberal project
because i think it's important to
recognize the um the full depth of the
american
project as not simply a liberal project
united state the united states has a
uh yes it's been dominated by a certain
form of
neoliberal capitalism um which has only
become more powerful in the last
several decades and maybe we're
witnessing its death throes now
um so yes liberalism and its
various uh manifestations
i think we have to say has been dominant
in the history of the united states but
there's a lot more going on here we have
our own homegrown socialist traditions
we have our own grown
fascist traditions uh and so it's
it's a diverse country and uh in terms
of the the philosophies and the
political theories that had been born
here on this
continent and i think there's there's
something uniquely
pluralistic about the united states that
makes it more difficult to succumb to
this these fantasies of racial purity
um that you know i don't want to accuse
dugan of that but
there are other folks they call
themselves third positionists
who are indulging in these fantasies and
many of them are european but they're
attracting more and more americans but
if you look at the history of the united
states of america what makes our
people unique what makes the american
spirit unique
uh yes it includes the contributions of
european cultures
but it also includes the contributions
of native americans
and african americans and asian
americans and latino americans all of
that
and it's not just a melting pot where it
all got squished together into an
amorphous blob
right the diversity in this country has
been allowed to
uh really it's struggled i shouldn't say
it's been allowed to but there's been
this struggle to maintain a sense of
the diversity the internal diversity
of our population and i think i don't
want to sound cliche but i do think that
is our strength but
the challenge is to maintain a sense of
civic identity
or national belonging at the same time
that we
provide for the freedom of individuals
and groups
to do their own thing um and right now
we're failing at that
we don't seem to i think we have a
constitutional
uh mechanism and an electoral process
that's
designed for the 18th century and we
live in a very different world right now
where um there are new forms of media
like i think the constitution was
designed for
um a media ecology of
of pamphlets and and print print media
right we've already gone through several
mutations in the media ecology since the
constitution was framed
and we're no longer really literate in
our consciousness
um we are digital in our consciousness
and
of course we all still know how to read
but
literacy has been subsumed first by
radio and then by television and now by
the internet
and so we need a different way of doing
politics now that the framers of the
constitution couldn't have imagined
um
and so you know whether or not
we're able to in some way hold together
as a country through this next election
or if there is some kind of a civil war
or continued spiral into
social breakdown and civil unrest
we may end up needing to call a
constitutional convention
to rethink the way that we organize
politically and that's a risky endeavor
because when you when you start to call
uh the established political order into
question then you know everybody has a
suggestion about how they want to fix it
or make it better
um but it may turn out to be inevitable
and
um i think we should be preparing now to
to think through
um how we can get beyond some of the
the divisions that are holding back our
spiritual development as a people
the two-party system the corporate
duopoly is certainly
holding us back right now um limiting
you know both of these parties are the
parties of property as gore vidal once
said
they're there to protect the ruling
class the interests of the ruling class
we don't have a populist party even
donald trump who pretends
uh to be for the working person is
himself just a fake billionaire
uh who wants to um
you know stay stay in with the the rich
people and
and the celebrities and he wants uh
to himself to be a celebrity and that's
all he he really cares about he doesn't
care about the working class
we don't have a party that cares about
the average person in this country and
so we need to really shake that up
and so the last piece here let's see
it's 5 57. i've already gone on too long
peter
so the last piece i just want to uh talk
about
is
what um the anthropocene means to me
in the context of trying to further the
spiritual mission of the united states
is deepening the sense of
pluralism that i think is basic to the
united states already
or should be so that it's not just a
pluralism
of human cultures or human ethnicities
but a
a pluralism also of all the other
species that call this planet home
and even further into a real sense of
ontological pluralism you know
liberalism and uh really all of
modernity
has had this vision
of the human being as something set
apart from the natural world
there was this division um
hewn between human society and
the natural world and human societies
were supposed to be
free or striving for freedom whereas
nature is just a deterministic machine
and they're for for the taking they're
to be turned into property so value can
be extracted from it
by human beings they're just as a
collection
of objects to be known and understood
and explained without remainder by
science
and exploited mastered by uh science and
technology
to serve human ends and that approach
to understanding the human earth
relationship
has been um wildly destructive
and now uh you know the chickens are
coming home to roost
and we're facing um
you know more hurricanes more wildfires
more droughts uh
and that's going to continue to worsen
as i was mentioning earlier leading to
mass migration
and so there's a need for us to really
um
break out of the anthropocentric and
sociocentric mentality
uh that modern people have grown so used
to
we're gonna need to learn to uh
to to inhabit this planet as
um as a diverse collection not only of
other peoples but of other species
other modes of existence and we're going
to need new forms of diplomacy
uh a new sensitivity to the interests
of non-humans um and my hope would be
that
you know william james in the
early 20th century gave a lecture called
the moral equivalent of war
and he was trying to find some
alternative to warfare that could unify
a people
unify not only nations internally but
human beings as a whole
and you know he he kind of he couldn't
have really foreseen the ecological
crisis coming but he
gestured toward the idea that conserving
the environment might be
the moral equivalent of war um and you
know even ronald reagan
once speculated about the need for some
external enemy
uh he thought it would be an alien
invasion to unite the human species
uh so the ecological crisis isn't
exactly an alien invasion because these
aren't
um life forms coming from another planet
their life forms
from this planet that we've been
ignoring for a while
and remembering that we share this
planet with them and remembering that we
have a shared interest
in cert and protecting certain forms of
life so that we can continue to
cohabitate here
i think might be a source of
unity for the human species
because you know ultimately i don't
think
we were meant to be uh i think it's
it's a it's a profound reduction of
human potential to imagine that the best
we can do is be a bunch of warring
tribes or warring races or warring
ideological
groups i think i'm not ready to give up
it's a faith i admit that something more
is possible for our species
and i think again just to reiterate the
particular
role that the american project has to
play in this is
enshrining these values of both
individual freedom and
social justice as
sort of orienting ideals that help us
move forward as a species protecting
diversity
while also ensuring uh
a sense of camaraderie and
and shared uh commitment
to life uh on this planet together
so
yeah there's so much more to say but
i'll leave i'll leave it there and uh
look forward to hearing comments and
critiques and questions
thanks for your attention cool so start
throwing your questions in the chats
uh i'll warm up matt with a question um
i think i saw in a conversation you had
with jeremy johnson
about the tension you personally feel
between being
a philosopher and wanting to be in that
state of unknowingness and at the edge
of one's thinking
but also being a political actor and an
agent in the world
and sort of like in order to be
successful in politics there has to be
some extent of rail politique you know
like it's like
you gotta be a little ruthless to get
things done especially when there's like
a sense of urgency
uh at hand um so how do you balance that
is this idea this that we have to kind
of be a little bit ruthless to get
things done by the same time we want to
hold on to these lofty ideals that
you know it's might be hard to achieve
well i mean my hope is that that the
politics of ruthlessness
is something that can be transcended and
i don't want to be naive about it but
um part of this deeper pluralistic
vision that um you know i've been trying
to articulate
here tonight and and then much of my
work as a philosopher for
the last several years it involves a
sense of political engagement as always
the practice of diplomacy and
a willingness to empathize with those
who
may at first appear to be enemies um
and so yes there's a there's a
machiavellian um you know power
dimension to the political arena and
i don't think we're just gonna be able
to get
you know move beyond that entirely um
and you know there are certain things
that i would be willing to
fight for um but at the end of the day i
think
my my philosophical side um
the the love of wisdom is is the abiding
value for me
even when i'm engaging in politics and
that means um
i don't claim to have uh to already be
in possession
of the truth and i know that i have a
lot to learn from
from others and so i think there's this
diplomatic mentality that i think if
if we were all able to cultivate might
enable us
uh to empathize with our political
enemies
so as maybe to come to understand that
we actually do share some interests
or that we could come to share some
interest through dialogue that we didn't
know we shared in advance of dialogue
so you know the cutthroat part of it i
think has reached such an extreme now
that everything has has grinded to a
halt and it's like we can't even do
politics anymore
we're on the verge of war so um
you know that's that's kind of how i try
to hold the philosophical and the
political together by
being diplomatic
and one thing i got and um which i get
from a lot of the people in the integral
and metamodern space which i agree with
is a need for like a transformation of
consciousness
um and
and i wanted something related to that i
wanted to double click on what you said
about
donald trump being a spiritual
opportunity because i wanted to write
this article one time called
calling trump the apex narcissist the
apex narcissist
is like his at one point his name was on
everyone's lips right so he's like
the most successful at being a
narcissist if you will um
and some some people were talking about
how he was uh that the heliote i think
kind of like the the sacred clown that
he's like
mirroring things to us that we don't
want to see in ourselves um
could you kind of speak more about what
you think that opportunity is and how
that relates to this transformation of
consciousness
yeah i mean um so we have a reality tv
star as our president now and um
everyone who identifies as liberal or as
a democrat
again yet they seem to blame trump uh
for all of the country's problems right
now
and there's almost this performative
dimension to
to hating trump i mean the folks on the
right call it
trump derangement syndrome and um rachel
maddow is like the ringleader and
you know i think there are plenty of
reasons to hate trump but
at the end of the day i it feels when i
step
back from the pageantry of our
two-party political system um
it all feels so performative to me and
almost like a kind of self-hatred
uh you know projecting one's own shadow
onto this
easy punching bag uh and like saying
things up
hating on trump is just so easy it's
just so easy and it doesn't you know
it's like at the end of the day
it's just it does nothing more than like
nancy pelosi
tearing up a speech uh you know at the
state of the union like that
is completely performative and
ineffectual it's not changing
uh any of the policies it's not dealing
with any of the corruption even the
whole
impeachment trial knowing in advance
that it's not going to go anywhere
because of the republican majority
what's the point it's a performance
right to make people think that there
are real divisions among the two major
parties
and don't get me wrong i don't think we
should collapse
the republican and democratic parties
i'd much rather have
a fascist enabling neoliberal in office
like biden
than a neo-fascist um and
that doesn't mean that you know if biden
is elected that
i would say the resistance needs to
continue um
because biden is only going to institute
neoliberal austerity
which is going to further inflame the
class divisions in this country which is
going
to lead to probably the rise of a
more intelligent more strategic
uh more eloquent trump 2.0
in four years you know so just because
we get rid of trump doesn't mean these
problems are going to go away
and the opportunity here again is to
recognize the shadow of this country
and to find some way of
of atoning for it and
unfortunately i mean there are small
signs here and there
of that happening but unfortunately you
know i can see
all of the legacy media major corporate
networks and the democrats
uh if biden manages to to pull this off
um it's just celebrating after the
election
uh as if now everything can return to
normal uh
and what a setback that would be if we
allow that to happen
um but for better or worse you know the
planet's not gonna allow us to return to
normal
um trump's supporters are not gonna
allow us to return to normal
and it's most likely we're gonna have a
contested election anyway so there won't
be much celebration
in the wake of the election there'll be
litigation and chaos
um but there's an opportunity longer
term i think for
it's almost like you know when a when a
when a white head forms and all the pus
gets to the surface of the skin and you
can just pop it and
release all of that um trump is kind of
like
uh i wouldn't say he's like
nothing against buttholes but he's not
the butthole of the country he's like a
pimple on the butthole in the sense that
uh
he's just a very small part of the
larger um
shadow and underworld dynamics that have
been at work in this country since
since the beginning since we first
failed to live up to our ideals
right pimple on a butthole that's that's
okay
yeah so i'm going to picture when i
watch the debate tonight
uh adithya you had a question
[Music]
you're on mute oh i need to give you
access to a mute yourself
uh yeah you can unmute yourself now
um thanks matt uh i think it's a really
beautiful provocation
that's how i take it with all of my
trigger um
i think i kind of was ushered into the
ideological project of america
growing up in our schools with american
exceptionalism and
have been disillusioned in many of the
ways that you
describe to the point where like it
doesn't feel like america is like
a feasible ideal anymore and and so
maybe some part of what's happening for
me and others is just
you know there's a sense uh do we just
give up on america
um is the runaway machine
of techno capital liberalism
out of control is it just you know is it
just a a sort of
dying holding chamber for us in which
case we
leave either psychically or physically
or you know we we if you read like hanzi
fry knocked in his second book he has a
special chapter on america which is
basically like
yeah don't worry about it like it's not
going to get to the end of the
democratic
the evolution of democracies you know
like you know
go cheer for the nordic societies or
other places and
you know if you're in america like you
know go to a farm and get your little
tribe together and do something cool and
you're
small and you know use maybe the the
roads infrastructure
internet money capitalism to just give
you a little safe spot
to make a mesh of these little you know
metamodern villages
around the world and and realize that
your real impact or influence is
elsewhere this is something very
appealing to me and i see it
contra posed against what you said as a
challenge it's like no well we're also
part of this
machine called america that is you know
barreling
towards destruction of the earth and
many other things
racial and environmental you know
injustice so is there anything that we
can do of course we're very small
you know agents in this um machine
um i think i i don't know if i have a
question so a lot of it
is a little bit of a reflection um i
think
i i'm hearing your provocation to sort
of like hey we're agents
and there's something that we can do
should do
you know morally or ethically are sort
of like uh
you know should be doing to
rescue the american ideal and i don't
know it's not i don't know if it's
believe in america is the right way of
saying it
but use our agency towards
um stopping this train wreck
maybe i'll just stop there because i
went quite quite a bit of a ways
but i'm curious if that uh registers
anything
yeah i'm definitely um i'm glad you took
it as a
as a provocation i i think i am
intending it to be so
and but at the same time you know it
could mean that
saving america means allowing for the
balkanization of
of the the republic in the sense that
there's more local autonomy
um more distribution of power away from
the central
federal government um
you know what do we need the federal
government for aside from
uh enshrining certain rights which i
think are important because
without this the federal government we
might still have slavery we might
you know we women wouldn't be able to
vote you know etc because there are
certain
i think states that may have held out a
little bit longer on some of those
things if not for the imposition of
federal power
um but then also there's the military
but if we can
find a way of enshrining i mean let's
let's just come on people let's get it
over with like
freedom and justice for all it's not
that hard
like we could do that um and then
with one one thing that really frightens
me about
um the devolution of power from the
federal level which
uh again one of the opportunities of
trump is like he's thrown such
such a wrench into the executive branch
and all the agencies overseen by the
executive branch there's been
such a brain drain of the the actual
competent people who were still in
government have fled
all these agencies whether it's the epa
or the state department or anyone else
and he's installed these political
figureheads um
you know at the heads of all these
agencies and i don't know that
the executive branch itself can recover
from that
the deregulation of the trump
administration
um and so it might be a good thing for
the
power to be more distributed among
states and municipalities but
what it's the pentagon that worries me
it's the national security state that
worries me it's this
giant aging military
behemoth that's full of
very traumatized and
increasingly suicidal soldiers
that's sucking up trillions of dollars
they don't even know where the money's
going i think they're just dropping it
out of airplanes over the ocean for all
we know
um and what is all that military power
gonna
where is it gonna go like these guys
these generals
they don't want to just let go of that
power you know
and so i worry about that but if maybe
we need some extraterrestrial help for
that i don't know but if we can deal
with that military issue
then um i do think it's probably a good
thing
for us to start thinking more locally um
you know return to the land start your
biodynamic farm
um and and try to eek out in existence
um that was more like the way things
were before the petroleum interval
because because that's coming to an end
and we need to figure out how it used to
be done
um hopefully we can still keep cool
things like the internet
maybe we can have some electric cars and
stuff but um
we're gonna need to change our lifestyle
like i
i don't know that dick cheney was the
first one to say this the american
lifestyle is non-negotiable
um but if it's not negotiable then we're
going extinct
pretty soon um
yeah can i follow up just on that um
briefly okay it's just a question around
um
it sounds like there's you know you're
talking about constitutional convention
so there's a kind of idealistic view hey
let's
actually recreate everything which kind
of seems like what hanzi might say
versus let's just gracefully dissolve
this thing called america let it
vulcanize take care of the military and
or some other things
let it die in a slow way so it doesn't
hurt the earth and that'll be our
spiritual
you know responsibility and we will have
done that so i'm just curious if you
have a
comment on that which one well i think
you could do both we could have a
constitutional convention to rethink the
constitution in even more federalist
terms
um where the federal government goes
even if we just reset the thing so that
the federal government has
the limited power that it used to have
you know and i think we do need though
ways to enshrine uh protection of
individual rights
and we need to enshrine some form of
environmental regulation that can't be
done locally because
you know watersheds and the atmosphere
and the oceans and stuff they don't
respect our borders
and so we need we do need some kind of
[Music]
i would like to see there be some kind
of a
governing structure that can help us
keep track of of things like that
um while at the same time as much as
of the decision-making and the economic
exchange that we can keep local we
should let be local
and corporate charter law
would definitely need to change i think
we need to
really rethink the way that we let
corporations come into local communities
and suck out all the money
um you know it's destroying
this country it's destroying the family
values
the local um
the localist values that conservatives
tend to have and why
they're the ones that are pushing the
capitalist machine
um so fervently when it's destroying the
family values that they
supposedly love and cherish i don't
understand
but uh you know i i think
i wouldn't want to have to choose
between a new constitutional order and
just this slow
i wasn't imagining it as just a decay
and a collapse
to localism as like the lowest common
denominator but we can intentionally
cultivate
that type of a society re-empowering
local communities
to make a lot of decisions themselves
and to
um you know i think we we should allow
for local currencies we can't
allow if congress is going to give over
its power to coin money
to quasi private central bank
we can't have a democracy we need to
allow every local community to have its
own currency
and you know you can exchange currencies
and stuff but i think
freeing up some of these old economic
ideas
would help foster the rebirth of that
kind of
rugged individualist american culture
that i do think
can be a gift that this country can
offer to the rest of the world
cool um elf you had a question
he's scrambling okay there you go sorry
it was more of a
statement than a question but uh yeah i
guess i was wondering
since we're talking about spirituality
why so much the focus is on politics if
you just look at a
an integral type framework not as the
law of the land but just as a framework
you see a lot in modernity
treating politics is kind of their new
alter or religion
you see trends in say a traditional
level
which used to be more religious with
kind of the q and on
phenomenon happening in postmodernism
you see
social justice warriors and i'm agreeing
with it
with some would call it anti-racist
religion i think it's interesting to see
how it becomes
dogmatic so i'm just curious i'll throw
the question then on
like where do you see the direction of
spirituality going
i think someone mentioned hanzi i think
he kind of points a direction there
of a secular pragmatic approach but just
curious what you think
i think one of the uh vicious
abstractions that
the modern world brought into existence
was this idea that we could somehow keep
church and state separate um as if
the private as if religion could just be
privatized
as a matter for the interior life of the
of the
individual private soul whereas
politics would be a domain where we
engage according to these purely
secular norms because we can see how in
practice that's never been
possible you know evangelical
christians certainly don't respect the
boundary between church and state but
nor do you progressive
democrats and black lives matter
protesters i think
are in a way um
[Music]
re-inventing christianity but without
god
in the sense of the real emphasis on
social equality uh
and and taking the side of the oppressed
i mean i hear jesus in
in a lot of what's being said with a
with a racialized
um some racialized language put on to it
but
it's it's um i think
you know blm in particular has um from
what i understand sort of been
um chosen by corporate america
uh to to play a certain role in
in this conversation to steer us away
from
questioning issues of political economy
that are at the root i think of of
racism in america and instead to focus
on
oh well let's just make sure that there
are more black billionaires or more
black corporate executives
or you know more black political leaders
in the democratic party
uh and you know i always think of that
line in childish gambino's song this is
america
um where there's a line where he's like
i think
he's saying his grandma i told him like
get your money black man and like so
black people want to be able to get and
participate fully in the capitalist
economy that they've been kept out of
for so long and i understand that but um
we need some alternatives
alternative sources of uplift than just
oh you can
have just as unlikely a chance of
becoming a billionaire as any white
person
in this new uh corporate approved form
of anti-racism i think we can do better
than that
um but yeah and i think
why if this talk was supposed to be
about spirituality am i talking so much
about politics well
i think we need to stop being in denial
uh about the the overlaps between um
the religious dimension of human
existence and
the political orders and forms of um
self-governance that we engage in like
if we don't have a if there's not a
spiritual
ideal that's motivating um our political
activity
then what is politics uh anymore um
we even if we pretend like it's for
those who pretend like politics is
purely secular
there's all these um all the trappings
of civic religion
to make us feel patriotic and we say the
pledge of allegiance and it
makes it ends up being a kind of
shallower form of religion
um and so why not just go all the way
with it and
you know then it's all it's it's not
like anything goes i think there's a
there's a need to find the deepest
spiritual impulse
that's at the base of all the world
religions that's that emphasizes
um love and emphasizes
um justice and and inclusivity so like
whether it's the hebrew prophets or the
teachings of jesus or
of buddha or the the real sense of
social um belonging that came along with
some of muhammad's ideas
um we need to draw this deep well
of of wisdom in search of of a planetary
spirituality that still i think can
preserve a lot of the religious
diversity
as long as we're connected at a deeper
substratum of our spiritual life
that connects us to these ideals
that's a good point with separation of
church and state i think many overlook
i guess just where i get caught up is
like you called it a political theater
and i couldn't agree more but
sometimes i think there's a yin and yang
component we need to do the inner work
as well
to then go to the marketplaces they
would say in zen so i think that's the
part that gets overlooked
you pointed too nicely with the shadow
but i'll shut up now so
let someone else get a question yeah
thanks alf
um so we're approaching our a lot of
time do you have maybe 10 minutes after
um to hang or do you have to leave no
i'm i'm good to go okay cool uh
nick you had a question
thanks peter so it's
hi matt um how
lodging abstractions like nationalism at
the heart of our identities
is not the root cause of the medic
crisis
and also a generator function of
self-termination
so given that nationalism is a
togetherness that generates alternative
theories of hierarchy dominance
exceptionalism and neo-colonial
practices
wondering how you can reconcile your
desire to preserve nationalism which is
what i'm hearing through your
argumentation
going forward with your concurrent
desire to hasten futures
where life is still a thing where you
know beings still exist
yeah well i think um
multicultural and even multi-natural
[Music]
nationalism is different than like an
ethno state
uh or an ethnic type of nationalism uh
multi-naturalism is a term
that the um anthropologist uh eduardo
viviera de castros has come up with
uh to emphasize the way that um nature
is not just some
finished unity but it's made up of a
proliferation of different organisms and
it's constantly
uh evolving and open-ended and so it's
it's his contrast to multiculturalism
which is a shallower form of pluralism
but
in any event yeah um if i thought that
human beings were
ready for to just leap into planetary
consciousness beyond
uh the more local attractors of a
nation-state then
then yeah let's go for it but i don't
think we're there yet
um i do think we need to avoid the
temptation of
um of of race-based
nationalism because race is another one
of those vicious abstractions that the
modern nature culture division has
foisted upon us
we're all more or less hybrids and
biology is way messier
than uh some of these race purists would
like to believe
um and so we need to avoid that kind of
reductionism
and think about and this is why i think
the united states of america is unique
in the sense that it's so
um pluralistic and multicultural from
from the beginning i mean
all the misfits from europe escaped over
here because of their crazy religious
ideas and the lack of tolerance for
those ideas back in europe
and they met uh when they got here a
plurality of
um indigenous peoples with you know
there were probably a thousand different
languages spoken on this continent
uh in 1500 um
one of the biggest tragedies of the
history of
of this uh continent post
contact with europeans is the um i think
we need to call it genocide even though
the majority of the death that happened
was a was a disease vector
and the europeans didn't intend that
they had no idea that they were bringing
these
old-world diseases that because of
cohabitating with animals for thousands
of years they were less
susceptible to but native populations
the statistic that seems to be most
well widely accepted now is between
1500 and 1650 or so about 90 percent of
the native population
died as a result of disease and being
enslaved and pushed off the land but it
was mostly disease
um and so but still there was a major
cultural transfer um
into those early uh settlers
from europe from the native americans
and um
the african slaves that were brought to
this country
uh also uh developed it's almost as
though
you know by the slavers allowed the
slaves to
practice christianity and then before
they knew it they started to get worried
because they were understanding the
teachings of jesus deeper than the white
people did
and i think there's a way in which the
the
promise of the united states is the way
that these
uh diverse cultural streams have have
uh flowed together to give rise to um
yeah a uniquely pluralistic conception
of what it means to be a human being and
in that context with that ideal
coming together as a nation to protect
that ideal
we you know we need to stop imposing our
version of freedom onto
other people in a militaristic way but
you know to be
um i don't think isolationism is a bad
word
when we're talking about the military i
want to be um
[Music]
open as a country culturally to to other
peoples
because that's that's the very i think
the nature of the american psyche
um is to be pluralistic in that way so
yeah it's nationalism it's maybe
patriotism would be a better term
for it but when it's rooted in this deep
not just multicultural but even a deeper
form of pluralism
i think it's less less dangerous than
maybe the
traditional forms of nationalism that
we've seen
so i have a million follow-up questions
but in the interest of placating peter i
won't ask you
thank you well feel free to email me or
well i'll be sure to leave my contact
info if you want to continue the
conversation
so we'll have um a readout maria's
question
and then maybe we'll end after that
so it would be interesting to hear you
out on the spiritual responsibility that
america has called upon itself through
modern colonization and through its
military
political cultural agenda throughout the
world it feels like there's a price for
such constant oppressive
agenda worldwide and i wonder how that
fits into this view
of a deaf new america
well i think the uh
you know after world war ii
um it's almost as though the united
states had to
[Music]
become the darkness that it was trying
to defeat
in order to defeat that darkness and
creating the military-industrial complex
to defeat the nazis
was a deal with the devil and that
military-industrial complex
was never drawn down it just continued
to expand and
um you know it's like
the nazis the americans beat the nazis
the american military destroyed fascism
in europe
and ended up doing what the fascists
were trying to do by creating this
global military empire
uh and
whether the nazi version of that global
empire would have been better than the
u.s version of that global empire i
don't know
um but uh as uh you know
i have my doubts but i don't think that
the american militarism
has anything um
[Music]
positive about it and it's been i think
um it's one of the
tragic sins of this nation uh you know
to use religious
language um to try to
[Music]
to dominate the rest of the world to
um to enrich ourselves i mean the the
we underestimate i think as americans
the
role that military imperialism
imperialism has played to
to maintain the the economy in this
country and the
value of the us dollar the u.s dollar's
value
is maintained by the threat of war
uh and you know why did we invade iraq
because saddam started trading oil in
euros
why did we go after gaddafi because he
wanted to create an african bank
and so i think
there's nothing about american
militarism that i would want to preserve
as we i'm trying to to shift
our our attention toward
a deeper
[Music]
source of ideals
that would be that if we stood true to
the ideals that we were founded upon
we would see how opposed they are to
this notion that
um america should be
imposing its version of
um of order upon the rest of the world
i really do think we need to clean up
our own act
and set an example um for others to
follow
rather than trying to force some
misconstrued idea on other
countries
okay um so let's
i think it's prudent in here uh matt is
there any kind of um
concluding thoughts or anything that
came alive for you throughout this uh
session today well i
i appreciate the opportunity to play the
role of uh
political propagandist i mean let's
let's be honest i feel like that's
that's kind of what i'm doing here and
i just want to say that um
[Music]
what i'm sharing with you guys it's not
like i
have uh certainty that this is right
um i i'm really trying to start a new
kind of dialogue about
a new way to imagine belonging to uh the
country
that we call america and it very well
could be the case that
um it's a lost cause
and so i just want to you know thank you
for indulging me
uh in this provocation and um
i've shared my email address if if you
had comments or questions that you
didn't get a chance to share
and uh you know i'm gonna keep having
this conversation
i'm curious to see how the debate goes
tonight
and um you know i just i just care
a lot about the potential that i think
this country has you know i study
american philosophy and american
literature and i
i feel like there is something unique in
the contribution that this people has to
make
to the world and i don't want that to be
lost i don't want it to be
completely overshadowed and tarnished by
by all the wrongs that this country has
done
so um yeah again i appreciate your
attention
and um i i want to encourage the stila
to keep hosting these
uh these dialogues it's it's amazing um
[Music]
the diversity of perspectives that
you're able to
mediate uh between here and i think
that's
that's part of what i'm talking about as
i think uh
a source of of hope that we can engage
in dialogue across difference
not so that we can all become the same
but so that we can
learn more about ourselves by
encountering
difference
beautiful so i'll make some closing
announcements in a moment but matt thank
you so much for
coming on the stoa um one thing i really
appreciate you about you is
and it shows this in the chat is your
ability to maintain
what i consider a true philosophical
disposition and temperament
yet at the same time explore and delve
into these
ideas that are important
in our present moment at the nice edge
so that being said let
us plug an event that is coming up in 20
minutes
uh painting with words loving
transformation or something with tim
adeline from the voice craft
collective this is going to be i don't
know what is going to be actually some
kind of like artistic conversation thing
i'm quite looking forward to it
so you can check that out and then uh
right after that
it's the the debate which i'm nervous
about i feel like it's gonna be a
show
but uh yeah so buckle up for that and um
i'll put some links in here to the store
anyways you know the drill store that's
here we have the patreon and the
sub stack so that being said matt
everyone thank you so much from the
store
thanks everyone